<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Articles on Slaveya.ink</title><link>https://slaveya.ink/categories/articles/</link><description>Recent content in Articles on Slaveya.ink</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://slaveya.ink/categories/articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Bulgarii “Kızılbaşi” sau “capetele roșii”</title><link>https://slaveya.ink/article/2022/03/30/bulgarii-k%C4%B1z%C4%B1lba%C5%9Fi-sau-capetele-ro%C8%99ii/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://slaveya.ink/article/2022/03/30/bulgarii-k%C4%B1z%C4%B1lba%C5%9Fi-sau-capetele-ro%C8%99ii/</guid><description>Un dans al capetelor roșii (sursă: O comunitate musulmană heterodoxă din Bulgaria fascinează și astăzi
Acest articol a fost publicat inițial pe Balkans in Site, un site grecesc dedicat Balcanilor.
Această denumire interesantă “Qizilbash/Kizilbash” (“capul roșie” în turcă) a apărut în jurul secolului al XV-lea, când adepții ordinului Safavid (dinastia Safavidă din Persia) au început să poarte pălării roșii distinctive cu douăsprezece raze – așa-numita “coroană a lui Haydar”.</description></item><item><title>Интервю пред Георги Кулов</title><link>https://slaveya.ink/article/2022/03/25/%D0%B8%D0%BD%D1%82%D0%B5%D1%80%D0%B2%D1%8E-%D0%BF%D1%80%D0%B5%D0%B4-%D0%B3%D0%B5%D0%BE%D1%80%D0%B3%D0%B8-%D0%BA%D1%83%D0%BB%D0%BE%D0%B2/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://slaveya.ink/article/2022/03/25/%D0%B8%D0%BD%D1%82%D0%B5%D1%80%D0%B2%D1%8E-%D0%BF%D1%80%D0%B5%D0%B4-%D0%B3%D0%B5%D0%BE%D1%80%D0%B3%D0%B8-%D0%BA%D1%83%D0%BB%D0%BE%D0%B2/</guid><description>Въпроси към Славея Неделчева
Г-жо Неделчева, през последните години темата за алевизма е популярна в България. Къде в момента е центърът на Бекташийския орден, който е стълб на алевизма?
През шестнадесети век привържениците на сефевидите и на други хетеродоксни религиозни движения са депортирани от Анадола в Румелия и интегрирани в ордена на бекташите, като по този начин се поставят основите за присъствието на шиитски ислямски елементи в Югоизточна Европа.</description></item><item><title>Bibliographic research on the European influences in the modern urban music culture in the Balkans</title><link>https://slaveya.ink/article/2022/03/11/bibliographic-research-on-the-european-influences-in-the-modern-urban-music-culture-in-the-balkans/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://slaveya.ink/article/2022/03/11/bibliographic-research-on-the-european-influences-in-the-modern-urban-music-culture-in-the-balkans/</guid><description>A project, that started in 2020 and was implemented by the Institute of Balkan Studies &amp;amp; Centre of Thracology of the Bulgarian Academy of Sciences (IBSCT-BAS), titled “European influences in the modern urban music culture in the Balkans. Bibliographic research”, made an important step towards the further research and understanding of the social and cultural history, processes of modernization in Balkan societies and history of music.
The main objective of this interdisciplinary project, funded by the Bulgarian National Science Fund (BNSF), was conducting a bibliographic study of European influences in the modern urban music culture in the Balkans.</description></item><item><title>Eastern Balkans StandWithUkraine</title><link>https://slaveya.ink/article/2022/03/06/eastern-balkans-standwithukraine/</link><pubDate>Sun, 06 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://slaveya.ink/article/2022/03/06/eastern-balkans-standwithukraine/</guid><description>Collection of information on behalf of Balkans in-site: Slaveya Nedelcheva &amp;amp; Theodora Vounidi
As the war in Ukraine unfolds and the whole world is astounded by its brutality and consequences, states are called upon to help in different ways and means. Mass rallies in support of the people of Ukraine, the end of the war, and the ouster of Putin are taking place all over Europe. The Eastern Balkans, Romania, Bulgaria, and Greece, quickly responded to the call for assistance at governmental and social levels.</description></item><item><title>Стихове на 6 езика</title><link>https://slaveya.ink/article/2022/02/18/%D1%81%D1%82%D0%B8%D1%85%D0%BE%D0%B2%D0%B5-%D0%BD%D0%B0-6-%D0%B5%D0%B7%D0%B8%D0%BA%D0%B0/</link><pubDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://slaveya.ink/article/2022/02/18/%D1%81%D1%82%D0%B8%D1%85%D0%BE%D0%B2%D0%B5-%D0%BD%D0%B0-6-%D0%B5%D0%B7%D0%B8%D0%BA%D0%B0/</guid><description>Трима автори, на 6 езика, ще бъдат представени в Арт галерия „Кръг“ по повод Международния ден на майчиния език.
В галерията могат да се видят рисувани пана с височина от 3 до 4 м с писани на ръка стихове на 6 езика на трима автори, родени в България. За двама от тях майчините езици са едновременно български и турски – Азиз Таш и Бехрин Шопова. Азиз Нашми Шакир-Таш е роден в Смолян, завършва „Арабистика” в Софийския университет, защитава докторантура в област „История на науките” в Истанбулския университет, сега работи в департамент „Средиземноморски и източни изследвания” към Нов български университет.</description></item><item><title>„The 43 Signatures”: Salvation of the Bulgarian Jews</title><link>https://slaveya.ink/article/2022/02/08/the-43-signatures-salvation-of-the-bulgarian-jews/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://slaveya.ink/article/2022/02/08/the-43-signatures-salvation-of-the-bulgarian-jews/</guid><description>The Holocaust in Bulgaria is the persecution and extermination of Jews in Bulgaria and in the territories annexed to it during the Second World War as part of the Nazi policy of “the final solution of the Jewish question.” Despite the fact that Bulgaria was an ally of Germany in the war, almost the entire Jewish population was saved. The Israeli Yad Vashem awarded 20 Bulgarians with the honorary title “Righteous Among the Nations” for the salvation of Jews during the Holocaust.</description></item><item><title>The Metaphor of the Rose and the Nightingale (“Gül-ü Bülbül”) in Sufi and Ottoman literature</title><link>https://slaveya.ink/article/2021/12/28/the-metaphor-of-the-rose-and-the-nightingale-g%C3%BCl-%C3%BC-b%C3%BClb%C3%BCl-in-sufi-and-ottoman-literature/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://slaveya.ink/article/2021/12/28/the-metaphor-of-the-rose-and-the-nightingale-g%C3%BCl-%C3%BC-b%C3%BClb%C3%BCl-in-sufi-and-ottoman-literature/</guid><description>The words “rose” and “nightingale”, widely used in oral and written Persian-Arabic literature since the early ages, began to be used also by Seljuk/Turkish authors at the end of the eleventh century and the beginning of the twelfth century, the early period of written Turkish literature. These metaphors were used by Sufi poets to describe religious mysticism, and authors outside of Sufi understanding used them to visualize the realities of social life and romance.</description></item><item><title>The Role of Bektashism in the “Awakening” and the National movement of Albania (19th and 20th century)</title><link>https://slaveya.ink/article/2021/11/29/the-role-of-bektashism-in-the-awakening-and-the-national-movement-of-albania-19th-and-20th-century/</link><pubDate>Mon, 29 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://slaveya.ink/article/2021/11/29/the-role-of-bektashism-in-the-awakening-and-the-national-movement-of-albania-19th-and-20th-century/</guid><description>The religious-philosophical ideology Bektashism originated and spread first in Asia Minor. There it was associated with the names of religious and political figures, poets, and writers such as Bektashi Veli, Balim Sultan, Gul Baba and others. Bektashi doctrines are characterized by Shiite and pantheistic character, although the influence of Shiites may be relatively late (sixteenth century). It is also believed that the Bektashi combined in their Order a significant number of doctrines and practices of diverse origins, including not only Shiism and Sufism, but also preserved pre-Islamic and non-Islamic beliefs and customs originating from Christianity and ancient religions, as well as ancient Turkic elements.</description></item><item><title>The Bulgarian “Kızılbaşı” or “the Red Heads”</title><link>https://slaveya.ink/article/2021/10/26/the-bulgarian-k%C4%B1z%C4%B1lba%C5%9F%C4%B1-or-the-red-heads/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://slaveya.ink/article/2021/10/26/the-bulgarian-k%C4%B1z%C4%B1lba%C5%9F%C4%B1-or-the-red-heads/</guid><description>This interesting name “Qizilbash/Kizilbash” (“redhead” in Turkish) appeared around the 15th century when the followers of the Safavid order (Safavid dynasty of Persia) started wearing distinctive twelve-gored red hats – the so-called “Haydar’s Crown”. Soon this headwear was abandoned, but the name “Qizilbash” remained. The name was originally a pejorative label given to the Alevi believers by their Sunni Ottoman foes, but soon it was adopted as a provocative mark of pride.</description></item><item><title>„Живот в кибритена кутия” Фатос Конголи</title><link>https://slaveya.ink/article/2010/03/18/%D0%B6%D0%B8%D0%B2%D0%BE%D1%82-%D0%B2-%D0%BA%D0%B8%D0%B1%D1%80%D0%B8%D1%82%D0%B5%D0%BD%D0%B0-%D0%BA%D1%83%D1%82%D0%B8%D1%8F-%D1%84%D0%B0%D1%82%D0%BE%D1%81-%D0%BA%D0%BE%D0%BD%D0%B3%D0%BE%D0%BB%D0%B8/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://slaveya.ink/article/2010/03/18/%D0%B6%D0%B8%D0%B2%D0%BE%D1%82-%D0%B2-%D0%BA%D0%B8%D0%B1%D1%80%D0%B8%D1%82%D0%B5%D0%BD%D0%B0-%D0%BA%D1%83%D1%82%D0%B8%D1%8F-%D1%84%D0%B0%D1%82%D0%BE%D1%81-%D0%BA%D0%BE%D0%BD%D0%B3%D0%BE%D0%BB%D0%B8/</guid><description>Фатос Конголи е роден в Елбасан, Албания. Работил е дълго време като журналист и редактор. Той е особено известен със своите романи, оценени от албанската и чуждата публика. Книгите му са публикувани във Франция, Италия, Швейцария, Гърция, Германия, Полша, Словакия, България и Сърбия. Три пъти печели годишната награда за най-добра книга в Албания, наградата „Велия”, също и най-високата литературна награда „Златно перо”(“Penda e Artë”). Оценен е като „Писател на годината” в Албания през 2006 година.</description></item></channel></rss>